<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Ens on Sigurd</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/en/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ens on Sigurd</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.127.0</generator>
    <language>En</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2024 18:44:17 +1000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/en/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Browned Butter Cookies</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/recipes/browned-butter-cookies/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2024 18:44:17 +1000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/recipes/browned-butter-cookies/</guid>
      <description>Ingredients Unsalted butter - 200g Sugar - 100g Brown sugar - 200g Vanilla extract - 2ts Large Eggs - 2 Flour - 300g Baking soda - 1/2ts Baking powder - 1/2ts Toffee candy bar - ~80g Chocolate - 200g Table salt Seasalt Method Cook 200g unsalted butter in a saucepan over medium heat, stirring often, until it foams, then browns. It should start to smell nutty. If it doesn&amp;rsquo;t smell any different than regular butter, let it cook longer.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neuron Segmentation</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/neuron-segmentation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/posts/neuron-segmentation/</guid>
      <description>Image: Scan of a part of nervous tissue. Bioscience Image Library, Fayette Reynolds.
During my final year of my computer vision degree, I wrote a paper titled &amp;ldquo;Know Your Neighbour&amp;rdquo;. In it, I highlighted how techniques in machine learning can be used to improve the efficiency of what&amp;rsquo;s called &amp;ldquo;3-dimensional neuron segmentation&amp;rdquo;, i.e, the process of identififying neurons in 3D space. Both me and my supervisor were very happy with the results, so I decided to write this blog, explaining what it is, how it works and what implications it can have for the future of neuroscience.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hi, human 👋</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jun 2024 21:47:21 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/about/</guid>
      <description>Photo: Me looking cool as a child.
My name is Sigurd and I&amp;rsquo;m a norwegian AI researcher, student and engineer. I currently live in Sydney, Australia where I&amp;rsquo;m earning a MSc Artificial Intelligence at University of Technology Sydney (UTS).
Did you know UTS has been named the third best university in the world for artificial intelligence? Source: US News Education
I grew up 78° north in Longyearbyen, Svalbard, a Norwegian archipelago close to the north pole where my father worked as a coal miner.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
